<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An address to the honourable city of London, and all other cities, shires and corporations, concerning their choice of a new Parliament together with a true character of popery and arbitrary government / humbly presented by C. B.</title>
            <author>C. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29005</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B40</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2639</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13174360</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13174360</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29005)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 445:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An address to the honourable city of London, and all other cities, shires and corporations, concerning their choice of a new Parliament together with a true character of popery and arbitrary government / humbly presented by C. B.</title>
                  <author>C. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Allen Banks,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98338:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98338:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ADDRESS To the Honourable City of LONDON, And all other Cities, Shires and Corporations, Concerning their Choice of a New Parliament. Together with a True Character of Popery AND <hi>Arbitrary Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly Preſented by <hi>C. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aude aliquid brevibus Gyaris, &amp; Carcere dignum</l>
                  <l>Si vis eſſe aliquid: —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rurſus amor Patriae ratione valentior omni.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cuncta prius tentanda, ſed immedicabile vulnus</l>
                  <l>Enſe recidendum. —</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>Allen Banks,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98338:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98338:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle Dedicatory, To all the Honeſt CITIZENS of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not unknown to the reſt of the Nation, how like your ſelves you have acted. What great things you have done for the Glory of God, and the Protestant Religion, for the Preſervation of His Majeſties Royal Perſon, and for the Peace and Safety of the whole Kingdom, is obvious to all perſons that have conſider'd your ſeveral Loyal Petitions to his Majeſty, and candid Applications to the late excellent Houſe of Commons: The juſt Harmony, and reciprocal Kindneſs betwixt your City and the Nations Repreſentatives, have given no ſmall Terrour to our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and no ſmall Comfort to our Friends. I need not trouble you with any further inſtance, how much your proceedings influence the Countries, more than by putting you in mind how the Papists thought to ruine them, by laying you in Aſhes. You are the only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Force that can oppoſe them, and You only can protect your Soveraign, as being the chief ſupport of the Government, the chief Refuge of the People, and the Curb or Bridle to the unjuſt illegal Ambition of all Arbitrary and Evil men: and this made thoſe Firebrands of the World, I mean the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> (of whom <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> prophetically ſpoke, when he wrote, <hi>Turba gravis Paci, placidae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mica quieti</hi>) firſt endeavour to compaſs your deſtruction, before they made any attempt upon the Perſon of the King. Your late eminent choice of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, as Mayor, Sheriffs, Recorder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath given much diſcontent to the Popiſh Party, who ſtand in need as well of corrupt <hi>Juries,</hi> as <hi>Judges.</hi> But above all, your moſt prudent Election of ſuch untainted Members to ſerve in the laſt Parliament, did render to other Corporations ſo worthy a Preſident, and your great Example was of ſo vaſt conſequence to the reſt of the Nation, that I may without flattery ſay, as we owe good Laws to a good Parliament, ſo muſt we in ſome meaſure attribute a good Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to your good City. And therefore, Gentlemen, although I addreſs this Paper to all other Cities, Shires, and Boroughs in general, yet more particularly to You, the honest Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Honourable Proceedings ſo highly conduce to the preſervation of that Church, that King, and that People, for either of which, I would most freely render my ſelf a Sacrifice; dreading no curſe like that of a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> and wiſhing no happineſs more then his preſent Majeſties long and proſperous Reign. Now as a Parliament muſt prevent the one, ſo does it at the ſame time help to preſerve the other, the King's Life being no longer in danger of the Papists, after once the <hi>Excluſive Bill</hi> is paſs'd. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the choice of this Parliament, depends the happineſs or miſery not only of his Majeſties Dominions, but of the whole Proteſtant Religion, and of all the Reformed
<pb facs="tcp:98338:3"/>Churches in Christendom: A good Parliament may be a means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the poor <hi>Hollanders</hi> from becoming an innocent Victim to all our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and preſent Evil Counſels, as well as <hi>Flanders</hi> and the whole Empire from being reduced to the <hi>French</hi> Yoke; after which, the ruine of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom would be an unavoidable conſequence: A good Parliament may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe his Majeſty to ſuch things as ſhall fortifie the Proteſtant Interest, and terrifie the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant into a greater moderation towards the diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>Hugonots:</hi> A good Parliament may retrieve the diſtreſſed Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> from that ſecond Popiſh Maſſacre which ſo daily threatens them: And laſt of all, as to our own Domeſtick concerns, a good <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament may ſecure us from our Enemies both abroad and at home; may encourage the Kings Evidence, after thoſe many Diſcountenances they have receiv'd as well from Proteſtants as Papists; may make it appear not only more honeſt, but more ſafe, to diſcover a Plot, then to contrive one; may remove thoſe diſtractions and fears which ſo daily amaze and threaten us; as alſo establiſh us in ſuch peace, tranquility and plenty, as may render us a fit object for the Envy of all Christendom. Therefore (Gentlemen) ſince providence (though against our wills) hath once more tranſmitted our fortune into our own hands, <hi>Let us not be weary of well-doing,</hi> but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Majeſty with no worſe a Parliament then the Laſt, who acted in all things for the glory of God, ſafety and honour of the King, and welfare of his three Kingdoms; in fine, ſuch a Parliament it was, that no one could except againſt, but ſuch guilty perſons, who justly merited their Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and for the ſame reaſon would decry all Parliaments whatſoever. And therefore if your Members be moſtly the ſame again, you do thereby expreſs that Gratitude, which they have justly merited from you by their former Services; as alſo juſtifie the prudence of your preceding choice: Neither is it a ſmall benefit to the Nation, if you elect ſuch men as are well acquainted with the manner of Proceedings in Parliament, and of whoſe integrity and prudence you have had a former tryal: this not being a time to enter Novices. However, to conſult the publick Intereſt herein is best; and in ſo doing, that God would endue you with the Spirit of Judgment, and direct you to all things that may be for the good of King and Kingdom, is the daily and hearty prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(Gentlemen)</salute>
               <signed>Your faithful humble Servant, <hi>C. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98338:3"/>
            <head>An Addreſs to the Honourable <hi>CITY</hi> of <hi>LONDON,</hi> and all other <hi>CITIES, SHIRES,</hi> and <hi>CORPORATIONS,</hi> concerning their Choice of a new <hi>PARLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hebr. 12.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Lest there be any praphane perſon, as <hi>Eſau,</hi> who for one Morſel of Meat ſold his Birth-right.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE many and eminent dangers occurring to this Kingdom of late years from its inteſtine Treacheries and Baſeneſs, have produced that conſternation, and that Jealouſie in the minds of all good people, as render them diffident both of their Friends and Fortunes, knowing no more which way to diſpoſe of their Eſtates, than their Affections: <hi>A Kingdom divided within it ſelf, can never ſtand:</hi> and this was our condition; when thoſe very men (the ſervants of the Publick) who ought to conduct and ſtand by us in the day of Battel, have been the Perſons in the World moſt likely to betray us, and lead us up like Sheep to the Slaughter. Thoſe <hi>Danbaean</hi> Senators, from whoſe Wiſdom ſo much was expected; thoſe Penſionary Tribunes of the People, in the late long Parliament, from whoſe integrity ſo much was hoped, have, inſtead of ſecuring that Peace and Tranquility, that Religion and Property which all good men wiſh'd for, not only diſturb'd the one, but hazarded ruining the other; <hi>Quid non mortalia pectora cogit, auri ſacra fames?</hi> our Temple of <hi>Janus</hi> ſeems to be already unlock'd, and we have every hour reaſon to expect the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould ſling open the doors: And then, if two or three hundred <hi>Dutch</hi> Mariners could preſent us with ſuch Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and apprehenſions, as we all know they did at their Arrival in <hi>Chatham</hi> River, how much greater now will our diſtraction be, when an Army of fifty or ſixty thouſand <hi>French-men</hi> is Landed amongſt us! When the Father muſt forſake his innocent and pretty Orphans, the Husband his diſconſolate and helpleſs Widow, leaving them to be murder'd by the Papiſts at home, whilſt he himſelf by his own death is compleating the Tragedy abroad! Are you not yet ſenſible of your condition? do you not yet perceive you approaching ruine? Think how the <hi>French King</hi> ſhakes his <hi>Faſces</hi> over us, when at the ſame time the Treacherous <hi>Papiſt</hi> renders us naked to his correction! Think how entirely your happineſs depends upon our Soveraign's Life;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98338:4"/>and then reflect upon the many Attempts there have been to rob us of that Bleſſing! Think how many good ſufficient Houſe-keepers have no ſooner committed themſelves and Families to reſt, but by that dreadful noiſe of <hi>Fire, Fire,</hi> (occaſion'd by ſome Jeſuitical Malice) have been waken'd from their innocent ſlumbers, juſt time enough to behold their <hi>All</hi> conſum'd in a few hours, which they with the Sweat of their Brows have been ſo many years ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring! Think how your Trading's loſt, and at the ſame time your Charges enereas'd, by keeping up a ſtanding Militia in your own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence! Think how your ancient Apoſtolick Religion, (for the which your Predeceſſors have not fear'd to die) is now upbraided and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Idolatrous Superſtition of an old Heatheniſh worſhip, under new Names, <hi>viz. Popery!</hi> Think how your Magiſtrates are murder'd before your eyes, for ſupporting that Liberty and Property whereby alone you ſubſiſt! That Property which entitles you to ſomething you may call your own, which having enjoy'd your ſelf, you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath to your Poſterity after you: That Property which ſatisfies your hunger and thirſt with wholſom and ſubſtantial food, as good Beef, Mutton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> meats unknown to any in an abſolute Monarchy, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the degree of the Nobility: That Property which gives you wherewithall to protect your Nakedneſs from the violence of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seaſons: That Property which ſubmits your Taxes and Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the will and diſcretion of your own Repreſentatives, who in all ſuch caſes have power to ſay, <hi>Hitherto ſhall you come, and no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> Alſo that Liberty which gives the Subject of <hi>England</hi> a fair and equal Tryal againſt his King, the Tenant againſt his Lord, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant againſt his Maſter; which preſerves unviolable the Rights of the meaneſt Peaſant, even in deſpite of the higheſt Prerogative; ſecuring both his Life and Fortune from all but the moſt juſt decree of twelve of his own Neighbours.</p>
            <p>When at the ſame time, your Neighbours in <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and other Popiſh Governments, have no other ſecurity either for their Eſtates or Beings, ſave the grace or favour of their Prince; which renders them and their Poſterity perpetual Vaſſals to the Crown. When in <hi>Sicily</hi> you may behold many hundred Acres of rich Soyl lie untill'd, by reaſon of the vaſt Impoſitions laid upon them by the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> When in <hi>France</hi> upon any Holy-day you may behold whole Troops of Farmers, begging the charity of Paſſengers as they travel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Road. Where their food and ſubſiſtance is, ſome courſe Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread, a few Onions, Roots, and Water: or if ever they become ſo wealthy as to purchaſe a ſmall Joynt of Meat, then preſently ſo much muſt be allow'd to their Prince for ſuch a prodigal debauch. When their Farmers have ſcarce Cloaths ſufficient to cover their Nakedneſs, being contented to go in Wooden Shoes, and all things elſe proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable; ſo that they are in a much worſe condition, than thoſe Poor to whom we pay Collection. When they can call nothing their own, ſince you may often ſee all that they have, to the very Cloaths on their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98338:4"/>backs, taken from them by an Edict or Proclamation: and this for no other end, then to ſacrifice them to the luxurious deſire of Glory, (or rather deſtruction of Mankind) ſo inſeparable from abſolute Monarchy. There you may ſee the poor Tenant ground to Beggary, betwixt the Tax-gat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erers on one hand, and the griping Landlords on the other. There you may behold the Merchants, Tradeſmen and Artificers, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exceſſive <hi>Gabels</hi> or <hi>Exciſe,</hi> almoſt as much as the Commodity it ſelf is worth, for every Egg or bit of Bread they put in their mouths. Their very Labours are not their own; their very Stocks are borrow'd of them by Privy Seals (which is but a civil way of Robbing) without any hopes of ever being paid again either Principal or Intereſt: their Houſes expoſed to Free-quarters; and what not? Nothing is more uſual than to ſee a Nobleman, with a whole Train of Horſe and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, ride over the poor peoples Corn when ready to Reap, and no man dares ask why they do ſo. Nothing more frequent then to have loaded Carts, Waggons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> compell'd to retire and give way to any giddy-headed Coxcomb on Horſe-back, that claims but the Title of <hi>Chevalier.</hi> Theſe and a thouſand more inconveniences are incident to Abſolute Monarchy, and Abſolute Monarchy incident to Popery; which is the only Reaſon that renders this Religion ſo amiable in the eyes of Princes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Rome Orbem domuit, Roman ſed Papa ſubegit:</l>
               <l>Viribus illa ſuis, fraudibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſte ſuis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now for you the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> give me leave to tell you, that in this Matter you are no leſs concern'd than the Commonalty, ſince the more you enjoy, the more you have to loſe: And I think you have no reaſon to queſtion, but that if once the Government of Parliaments be ſupplanted by the Sword, you would ſoon be reſolv'd into the Body of the Commonalty; for I never obſerv'd a Red-coat in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s ſtanding Army, that ever made any difference between a Lord's Houſe and the meaneſt Farmer's; neither do I believe, that if there were no Parliaments, the priviledge of Peerage would long fignifie any thing. And as for the Gentry, I know no priviledge they could pretend to, why their Eſtates ſhould be leſs obnoxious to Taxes, than thoſe of the meaneſt Commoner; however, if they ſhould be more favourably dealt with, it is but the Prince's courteſie, which he may continue or abrogate at his pleaſure. Therefore the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern is univerſal, and he who betrays it, is no leſs a Traitor to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in particular, than to his Country in general.</p>
            <p>Having thus therefore expoſed thoſe misfortunes which ever attend upon Popery and Arbitrary Government, give me now leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to your more ſerious conſideration ſome remedy, whereby you may at leaſt hope to aſſwage the grief, if not to perfect the cure, of what you ſo much fear: And this can only be done, by ſearching to the bottom of our evils, <hi>Radicem petere,</hi> by retiring from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent to the cauſe, wherein, I fear, we may diſcover ſome Members of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98338:5"/>the late Long Parliament to have acted a conſiderable part, being themſelves the acceſſaries, but thoſe that choſe them the principals of all our preſent evils.</p>
            <p>As we now have, ſo heretofore all other Nations had their <hi>Ordines Regni,</hi> or <hi>States,</hi> though diſtinguiſht by different Names, ſuch were the Fathers of Families, and Princes of Tribes among the <hi>Jews;</hi> the <hi>Ephori</hi> among the <hi>Lacedemonians;</hi> the <hi>Senate</hi> among the <hi>Romans;</hi> the <hi>Forum ſuperbienſe</hi> among the <hi>Arragonians;</hi> and now the <hi>Dyet</hi> among the <hi>Germans;</hi> all which in <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> are comprehended under the Name of <hi>Parliaments.</hi> But however the original inſtitution of theſe were for one and the ſame purpoſe, <hi>viz. Salus Populi,</hi> the preſervation of the people, as being all Governments of the mix'd or <hi>Gothick</hi> Model; yet they have moſt of them loſt both their form and ends, for the which they were at firſt deſign'd, being ſubverted and degenerated, ſome into Republicks, as part of <hi>Italy,</hi> others into Tyranny, as <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> where, by the cunning and addreſs of ſome of their late Princes, by the ſervility and folly of the Nobility and Gentry, by the ſuppleneſs, treachery and fawning of the Clergy; as laſtly, by the Ignorance and ſtupidity of the common people, in thoſe Kingdoms where Popery had ſo long prevail'd, (in firſt giving up the power they had of raiſing Taxes, whereby their conſent to the making of Laws was quickly after thought unneceſſary) they are reduced to that paſs, that their Parliaments are only to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute that Law which the King himſelf makes, to raiſe that Tax with the King himſelf levies, having a propriety in nothing but their own ſlavery. So that <hi>England</hi> at preſent ſeems to be the only place, which retains its primitive method of Rule by Parliaments, who (according to their firſt inſtitution) ſerve as Council for the King, and Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates for the People; and this when duly executed, without any fraud or partiality on either ſide, may be properly call'd a mixt or limited Monarchy, wherein the King hath his ſhare in the Government, and (ſubordimate under him) the people theirs, being undoubtedly (when each move regularly within their own Sphere) the beſt Conſtitution for the good of both, that is yet extant in any part of the known World, provided it could always remain as it now ſtands, wherein we participate of the good, without any of the ill of all other Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But when either ſome diſaffected Miniſter with the Prince, or ſome factious Subject with the people, ſhall out of their own private ends occaſion a ſeparation or different intereſt between them, then the Game being once begun, if the Court Suit turns up Trump, we hazard running into a Tyranny and Popery; if the peoples, into a Republick and Presbytery; both which evils proceed from one and the ſame venomous humour, only differing as the Plague and the ſmall Pox; where, in Popery as in the Plague the venom reſorts all into one <hi>Bubo,</hi> the <hi>Pope;</hi> when in Presbytery, like the ſmall Pox, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy or virulent matter is more diſperſt into ſeveral little <hi>Puſtles</hi> or <hi>Elders,</hi> which therefore renders it the leaſt dangerous of the two.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98338:5"/>I cannot but be ſenſible; that to commend to <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men the preſent Government under which we live, and that wife Inſtitution of the <hi>Great Council,</hi> (as it was anciently,) or Parliament, (as it is now call'd;) ſome may think as needleſs, as to praiſe the uſefulneſs and neceſſity of the Air we breath; ſince as we owe our ſubſiſtence to the one, ſo ought we to attribute all our happineſs and well-being to the other; For that it is this Conſtitution, this conjunction of King and People, that hath in ſo many Ages preſerv'd us from being expos'd to the Arbitrary will of <hi>one ſingle perſon,</hi> who though he may happen ſometimes to be wiſe, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and juſt, yet that is but caſual, ſince in moſt private Families there are ſeen two deſcents of raſh, prodigal and voluptuous Heirs, for one that is ſober, prudent and thrifty. It is this that hinders the Subject from being given up as a Prey, not only to the will of the Prince, but (which is ten times worſe) to the unreaſonable paſſions and luſts of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, chief Miniſters and Women, when Inſtead of a Monarch, (who Governs but in Name, as it often happens) be ruled like the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>French,</hi> by an inſolent <hi>Major</hi> of the <hi>Palace,</hi> who will be ſure to mind the private intereſt of himſelf and family, ten times more than that of the Prince, or the publick Good; or like the <hi>Turkiſh Empire,</hi> under a weak <hi>Grand-Seigneur,</hi> by the prevailing Concubine of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> who is perhaps her ſelf manag'd by no higher dictates than that of her <hi>chief Eunuch,</hi> or <hi>ſhe-Slave.</hi> I ſhould not ſpeak a word in a Subject ſo evident and perſpicuous, did I not obſerve the impotent Ambition of ſome men, who care not (provided they may trample upon, and domineer over their inferiours,) how much their ſuperiours do the like over them, their ſouls (like moſt inſolent mens,) being mean enough to ſubmit to it; or elſe through the ignorance and ſtupidity of ſome lazy inſignificant Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, who care not how things go, provided they may enjoy their Hawks, Hounds, or Bowling-green meetings; and for Politieks, are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by their <hi>more impertinent Chaplain,</hi> or Parſon of their Pariſh. Did we not (I ſay) daily ſee the Deſigns of ſome idle, covetous and ſyco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Clergy-men, who like Ivy, though it cannot grow without the ſupport of the Oak, and yet will deſtroy it at laft, do in private Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, over a Glaſs of Ale, as well as in their Pulpits, over their Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, ſet up abſolute Monarchy to be <hi>Jure Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> declaiming againſt the unreaſonable ſtubbornneſs of any Parliament, that will not give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the peoples money, and ſubmit themſelves to be fleec'd, as often as the chief Miniſter or Favourite thinks fit. They cry up the Prince like an Angel, ſo long as he will be their Executioner, to whip, impriſon or hang all that are not of their flock; or refuſe to give up their Souls, once again to be managed by an implicit faith, whereby in the mean while they might not be troubled with thoſe uneaſie tasks of Studying, Preaching and Catechiſing, but may have nothing elſe to do only to live at eaſe, keep their Coach and Horſes, with a Curate to do all the drudgery, whilſt they are making their Addreſſes above, by flattering and informing at ſome great Nobleman's or Biſhop's Table; or elſe if their parts reach ſo high, by ſome ſycophant Pamphlet or Sermon againſt the Government eſtabliſh'd by Law, they teach that men have no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98338:6"/>either in their Lives or Goods, but during the Prince's pleaſure. It would be a tedious buſineſs, nor is it the deſign of this paper to repeat or Anſwer all their ſilly futillious Arguments upon this Subject; it is ſufficient to tell them it can be eaſily proved, that the Inſtitution of the <hi>Wittena Gemots</hi> or Great Councils, were more ancient than Chriſtianity it ſelf, amongſt our <hi>Saxon</hi> Anceſtors, and conſequently that the People had their Repreſentatives in thoſe Aſſemblies, before the Biſhops or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Clergy were ſo much as heard of in this Iſland, as Mr. <hi>Petyt</hi> in his late Ingenious Tract hath made appear; and that <hi>Tithes</hi> (their <hi>Diana</hi>) were granted by King <hi>Ethelwolf, (Anno</hi> 885.) in a general Council of <hi>Earls,</hi> great men, and an infinite number of other <hi>Liege</hi> men of the whole Land: <hi>Vid. Spelmans Councils, fol.</hi> 348. This is but a Taſte of thoſe many Preſidents, which have been collected by learned Pens upon this Subject; therefore I ſhall ſay no more to theſe Gentlemen, but hope, that if ever their ſo much deſired abſolute Monarchy get uppermoſt, they may every one of them be obliged to maintain (as <hi>William the Conqueror</hi> made the <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Ely</hi>) upon free Quarter, a Trooper or Red-coat at leaſt, to fight, as well as a Curate to Preach for them, out of their fat Benifices and Pluralties.</p>
            <p>Since therefore at preſent we live under ſo happy a Government, where being ſecurely landed our ſelves, we behold the Shipwrack of our Neighbours; and ſince notwithſtanding the goodneſs of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, (who (I hope) deſires nothing leſs than the alteration or ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that Government, which as well by his Coronation Oath, as by his own Lenity and good Nature, he thinks himſelf oblig'd to preſerve;) There are yet ſome, who out of their own private ends, endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move our ancient Land-marks, introducing Popery and Slavery amongſt us. Since therefore it is ſo much the Intereſt of all true <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men to maintain theſe Priviledges, conveyed from their Anceſtors through ſo many Generations inviolable, upon which all our happineſs, ſafety, and well-being depends, I think no man in his Senſes, but muſt confeſs, that the right way to manitain the end is to look to the means, and that is, by taking care what perſons they chooſe for their Repreſentatives, with whom alone they muſt truſt their Eſtates, Lives and Liberties. Now this Government by Parliaments, however according to its primitive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution it was the beſt of all others, yet as well in that, as in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, there hath been found out ways of corruption, and that is when either they ſit too long, too ſeldom, or are too frequently Diſſolv'd, for that too frequent Diſſolutions are no leſs dangerous to the Subject than too long Seſſions; nevertheleſs it may be in the Electors power to avoid the inconvenience of both, and that by making a good choice. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if the Country people will ſell all that they have for a Glaſs of Sack, or a pet of Ale, chooſing him that will give them moſt Drink to day, though they know him to be a perſon who will ſell both their Religion, Lives and Fortunes to morrow, then ſuch frequent Diſſolutious, muſt of neceſſity Ruin us; for that the honeſt Country-Gentleman, deſigning no other private advantage, but the true Service of his King and Country, hath no reaſon, neither is he able, once in half a year to ſpend 4 or 500 pounds, only to purchaſe a place full of charge, trouble and danger
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98338:6"/>without any profit to himſelf, only to ſerve thoſe who put him to ſuch an unkind expence. Who ever knew a Coach man or Groom buy his place, unleſs he deſign'd to rob his Maſters Bin? And the caſe is the ſame; for no man can afford to bid ſo high, as he that deſigns to make money again of his place. The <hi>Italians</hi> have a Proverb, and 'tis a true one, <hi>That he who buys Justice must ſell it again.</hi> Therefore whoever you put to Charge in your Elections, blame him not if he makes money again of what he bought, for that you did not lend him your Truſt, you ſold it him, and what a man hath purchaſed with his own money, he may lawfully ſell again. Now that man who does wilfully give his Voice for a knave or Fool, doth his endeavour to Ruin both his Country. Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Poſterity, and to be as bad or worſe than the perſon he chooſes; when if the greater part of the Houſe be Wiſer or Honeſter, it is no thanks to him; and for his part, if none elſe were concerned with him, it were no matter if he were made a Slave to morrow, eſpecially, ſince he cannot but be ſenſible how many have already declar'd, that they would ſell their Country for a morſel of Bread; (for I look upon any conſideration, though it be an Office or Penſion in the Cuſtom-Houſe of 2000 pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> as no better in Ballance with that) ſo as if a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of ſuch men ſhould get into the Houſe (and we know that the children of darkneſs are wiſer in their Generation than the children of light) in what a miſerable condition were this poor Nation in at this Juncture of time? The old <hi>Lord Treaſurer Burleigh</hi> (who is thought to have been the greateſt States-man that ever this Nation bred) did fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently deliver as a Maxim, or rather as a Propheſy, <hi>That</hi> England <hi>can hardly be undone, unleſs it be by her own Parliaments,</hi> undoubtedly foreſeeing that all other Oppreſſions as being wrought by Violence, might perhaps by Violence be in time ſhaken off again? whereas when in a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary way we are undone by a Law, that can never be reverſt but by a down-right Rebellion, becauſe the Parties advantaged by that Law will never agree to the repealing of it; and a Rebellion is both ſo dangerous and of ſo black a Character, as men either Rich or Conſciencious will hardly engage in it; and therefore no publick miſchief is ſo irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as that which is grown into a Law, and that cannot be impos'd but by a Parliament. Wherefore as we tender our Religion, Liberties and Eſtates, we muſt (as much as in us lyes) chooſe a good Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, ſince there never was a time wherein we more needed men of Wiſdom, Courage and Integrity, who will not quit their Duty, either for want of conſideration, for favour, reward or fear. The firſt and ſecond of theſe Accompliſhments I ſuſpect not, for that in ſuch a numerous Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly there cannot want ſome wiſe bold men, who will be able to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and inſtruct the reſt: therefore I need only ſpeak to their want of Integrity, or corruption from private Intereſt, which uſually proceeds either from fear of loſing what a Man now enjoys, or hope of gaining what he yet has not. For though men may talk high, and keep a great noiſe with Conſcience, and Love to their Country, yet when you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand mankind aright, (not as it ſhould be, but as it is, and ever will be) then will you find, that private Intereſts is the ſtring in the <hi>Bears</hi> Noſe;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98338:7"/>it is that which governs the Beaſt. Therefore by this Obſervation we may gueſs, who are fitteſt to be choſe Members of Parliament, and who are not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Avoid all ſuch as hold any Office of conſiderable value during pleaſure,</hi> they being ſubject to be over-aw'd. For although a man wiſh well to his Country, and in the betraying thereof knows that at the long run he miſchieves his poſterity, if not himſelf, yet the narrowneſs of mens minds is ſuch, as makes them more tenderly apprehend a ſmall preſent damage, than a far greater hereafter. Such men muſt of neceſſity be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a great temptation and diſtraction, when their Conſciences and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt look different ways, eſpecially having obſerv'd ſome men turn'd out of their Employs, after voting for the Intereſt of their Country, as Mr. <hi>Garraway</hi> was. Therefore ſince theſe men know before-hand the Inconveniencies, that attend the Truſt of a Member of Parliament faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſcharg'd, 'tis very ſuſpicious and reflecting upon their honeſty, if any ſuch ſtand; and I think we are bound in Charity, nor can we do them a greater courteſie, than to anſwer their Petition in the Lords Prayer, Not to lead them into temptation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Suſpect all thoſe</hi> (men of ill repute) <hi>who in their Profeſſion or near Relations have any dependency upon the Court;</hi> for they (unworthily) gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing at the King by themſelves, are apt to vote right or wrong, as they imagine will moſt pleaſe the Prerogative party. And perhaps this fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy helpt the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> to that favour, which hindred him from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon his Trial the former Seſſions. It is a hard matter for a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier to pleaſe that Miniſter who ſupports him, and thoſe whom he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents at the ſame time; and if he endeavours to oblige both, he becomes ſuch an uncertain Weathercock, as moſt commonly he pleaſes neither. Wherefore the moſt prudent and honeſteſt of the Courtiers are obſerved to decline being Parliament-men, for this very Reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Suſpect all ſuch as ſpend much upon you in Entertainments at their Elections:</hi> for that (as I told you before) he who buys any Office, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to make Money of it again. And then conſider with your ſelves, what Looſers you will be, if to laugh and be merry one day, the Perſon you chooſe ſhould give You and your Children occaſion to mourn for ever after! Think how juſtly the ancient Heathens may upbraid this baſeneſs of us Chriſtians, when, as they ſacrificed many of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nay, and oftentimes their own Lives for the good of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; ſo on the contrary, do we ſacrifice both our Religion, Lives, and Country, for the pleaſure of one days debauchery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, Shun all ſuch men as are deſperately in Debt;</hi> for they needing Protection from paying of their Debts, are ſo afraid of being Diſſolv'd, as makes them ſubmit to any thing, rather than be left to the unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Rage of their hungry Creditors, who have ſo long faſted for their Money. For all ſuch Perſons (though ſome of them may be look'd upon as honeſt fair-condition'd Gentlemen, and good Houſe-keepers) are in danger of being tempted to repair the decays of their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Fortunes, by the Ruine of the Publick. Moreover, the chooſing of ſuch broken Fortunes, undoes Trade, ruines whole Families, and I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98338:7"/>have known it drive many men (contrary to their own inclinations) to wiſh never to ſee Parliaments more in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly, Avoid all ſuch as have been known Favourers of Papiſts; or Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Friends to any of the Lords in the</hi> Tower; <hi>Nay beware of any that ſhall be recommended to you by ſuch as are ſo,</hi> (let them be never ſo Great men in your Countries) unleſs you intend to have their Friends to be their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. For when any perſon ſhall out of a private Intereſt of his own, Elect, or give his Voice for one who is either a Friend or Relation to <hi>Him</hi> that ſtands Impeach'd by all the Commons of <hi>England</hi> of High-Treaſon, he does in ſuch a Caſe, as much as in him lies, endeavour to deſtroy the Kingdom, by ſaving the Life of its Enemy; for that if all other Electors ſhould do the ſame, he might live to perfect that Ruine amongſt us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which otherwiſe he muſt leave unfiniſhed: An Act no leſs unnatural, than for a man to ſell a Pardon to him that murder'd his own Father! It the former wiſe Parliament thought it reaſonable (as they did) to Vote <hi>him a Betrayer of the Rights and Priviledges of the Commons of England,</hi> who ſhould dare to plead at Bar in behalf of the Earl of <hi>Danby;</hi> let not thoſe who chooſe his neareſt Relations and Friends for his Judges, think themſelves leſs faulty than he that ſhould have pleaded for him after the aforeſaid Vote, ſince the deſign of both is the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſaving of his Life. Therefore if any do ſo, may their ſhame be their confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly, Above all others chooſe not any of thoſe who have been juſtly pointed at by the name of Penſioners,</hi> as being the worſt and baſeſt of Traytors; who making Shipwrack of all Honour, Honeſty, and good Conſcience, ſell their Votes for Offices preſent Gratuities, or conſtant Penſions. The firſt notorious brood of theſe Vermin, were in the Old Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment called by the name of <hi>Self <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eekers;</hi> but the late <hi>Lord Treaſurer</hi>'s Creatures were in greater numbers, more voracious, and of more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Obedience, or as the <hi>French</hi> call it, <hi>Sans Reſerve.</hi> They by the former excellent Houſe of Commons, are for their <hi>Secret Service</hi> branded by the open name of <hi>Penſioners,</hi> which they will hardly claw off notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Parliaments Diſſolution, hath, as yet reſcued them from other puniſhment. However, that the Populacy might not ſplit twice upon the ſame Rock, my requeſt is, that before they go to any Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they would peruſe Sir <hi>Stephen Fox</hi>'s Catalogue both of ſuch Perſons and Sums as he recollected in his memory, without the help of his Books which upon ſome weighty Reaſons (above us Vulgar peoples ſearching into) was denied him. Now this <hi>Penſionary</hi> Inſtitution of the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, was certainly of great advantage to himſelf, and moſt pernicious to <hi>England;</hi> for if he did really diſtribute ſuch ſums as is pretended, then he might in a ſhort time make and repeal what Laws he pleas'd; or if he did not diſtribute them, then to his own enriching, he might by an untrue accompt, divert a vaſt Treaſure into his own Purſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly and Laſtly,</hi> As for you Citizens, Burgeſſes, and Freemen of Corporations and Cities. I ſhall ſay but little to you in particular, more than what hath been ſaid already in general; only, <hi>whoever is u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be choſen Knight of the Shire, is likewiſe unfit to be choſen a Burgeſs.</hi> Neither let the more ſpecious pretences of any man, (that ſhall promiſe to build
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98338:8"/>you a Town-Hall, or relieve your Poor with Mony, (or out of his adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Woods) deceive you any longer; for if ſo, wherein are you better than your Horſes, whom you catch every day, and clap a Bridle into their Mouths, only by ſhewing them a few <hi>Oats,</hi> which they are never like to Eat Even the very Mice are too wiſe to be taken by an old Bait, but will firſt have the Trap new baited, before they'l meddle; and yet I have known a Corporation, which has been taken twice by the ſame Bait But however ſuppoſe theſe men do really perform what they promiſe, what compenſation is that, if that the men you chooſe ſhould lay a good ſwinging Tax upon your Eſtates, without any real cauſe; or ſhould give up the very Power you have of Taxing your ſelves, or ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Repreſentatives in Parliament. (for one bad Parliament may ruine us,) what good would the Mony for your Poor do you in ſuch a caſe, more than when you thereby reduced to Beggery, you might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps your ſelves (the Gentry of the Country having no reaſon to relieve you) be forced to come in for a ſmall ſhare of this their Hypocritical Charity: An excellent reward for Folly. Neither ſay, Oh, this is but one man, and can have but one Voice; he will do our Town a great deal of good, and can do us but little hurt if he would. For that, firſt, one or two Voices have ſometimes carried a Vote of great importance: and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, you know not the bad example this may give to other Neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Corporations, and if all ſhould do ſo, in what a miſerable caſe would you be? ſince the Voices of the Burroughs make two thirds of the Houſe. Laſtly, no man can tell the influence that one cunning talkative man hath over the reſt of the Houſe, eſpecially over thoſe that weigh Words, more than Reaſon or Senſe. But I ſhall ſay no more upon this ſubject, only deſire you to remember <hi>Eſau,</hi> who ſold his Birth-right for a meſs of Pottage, and could never afterwards recover it, though he ſought it with Tears: Alſo, when once you had Elected ſuch a corrupt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no Prince (but ſo juſt and gracious a Prince as ours) would ſuffer you to get rid of 'em in haſt, or at leaſtwiſe till they had done your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for you.</p>
            <p>Having thus therefore ſhew'd you what perſons you ought not to chooſe, ſo now in the next place, the more clearly to perceive what kind of perſons our preſent neceſſity requires to be choſen, conſider for what ends they ſerve, and they are two: One is, the preſervation of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion from <hi>Popery;</hi> The other is, to preſerve inviolably our <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Properly,</hi> according to our known Laws of the Land, without any introduction of that abſolute and arbitrary rule in other Countries, which we are neither to imitate or regard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Therefore as near as we can gueſs, <hi>we ought to elect good Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants towards God and juſt towards Ma.</hi> But foraſmuch as in this corrupt Age wherein we live, men are not ſo ſpiritual as they ought to be, it is not amiſs to ſeek for thoſe, whoſe ſpiritual intereſts is ſeconded by a temporal one. Wherefore the ſureſt Champions for our Religion againſt the Papacy, are our <hi>Abby land d-men;</hi> for notwithſtanding the regiſtred Diſpenſation to <hi>Harry</hi> the Eighth from the Pope, for the ſeizing of thoſe Monaſteries and Lands, yet of late they pretend that the Pope had not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98338:8"/>power to alien them from the Church; wherefore the preſent poſſeſſors can never truſt or rely upon any new Promiſes or actual Grants thereof, eſpecially from him whoſe everlaſting and declared Maxim it is, <hi>Never to keep Faith with hereticks.</hi> Undoubtedly to make eaſy his aſcent into the ſaddle, he will proffer many Aſſurances and Grants; But if theſe Abby-landed men be not the moſt ſilly of all others, they will never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him; for when he is once firmly ſettled, then will with his Canon-Law diſtinctions, like Fire under Quick-ſilver evaporate away all his promiſes, and violently reſume the Lands, glorifying in his own Bounty, if he require not the mean profits: — <hi>habeat jam Rome Pudorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> For our Liberty and Property, <hi>men of fair Repute in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, are of all others moſt likely to prove the stouteſt Patriors, eſpecially if in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion or Reverſion they are men of good Eſtates;</hi> for their Concern is the greater: And we find by experience of ſuch as Travel into forreign parts, where themſelves have no Eſtates, <hi>Faſcile habetur paupertas ſine damno;</hi> and accordingly when War and Confuſion begins to ariſe, they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it not with the hundredth part of that anxiety, as they would do if the like ſhould ariſe at home, where their whole lively hood is at ſtake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly and laſtly, I conceive it will not be amiſs, if for the moſt part you chooſe the ſame Members again that ſerz'd you faithfully the laſt time;</hi> ſince in ſo doing, you will both take off that fear of Diſſolutions, which is of ſuch fatal conſequence in a Parliament, as alſo oblige them to ſerve you more chearfully ever after, when you have ſo highly honoured them twice. Now to this purpoſe, give me leave here to inſert a Preſident worthy both the Conſideration and Imitation of all the Shires and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations in <hi>England;</hi> It is a moſt generous Letter written (ſince this late Prorogation to Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Calverly</hi> from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Burgeſſes of <hi>North-Allerton</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> (Dated <hi>Jan.</hi> 14.) in theſe Words:</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> The unexpected and ſudden News of this days Poſt preventing us from thoſe due acknowledgments, which the Greatneſs of your Services for Publick Good have merited from us, we have no better way (now left us) to expreſs our Gratitude and the high reſentments of your Actions before, and in the laſt Seſſions of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, than to manifeſt our approbation thereof, by an Aſſurance that if a Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of this preſent Parliament happen, (ſince you have evidenced ſo ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your affection to His Majeſties Royal Perſon, and your endeavours for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Proteſtant Religion, our Lives and Liberties,) we are reſolved (if you pleaſe to comply with us) to continue you both as our Repreſentatives, and do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore humbly beg your acceptance thereof; and father, that you will continue your Station during this Prorogation, faithfully aſſuring you, that none of Us deſire to give, or occaſion you the Expence or Trouble of a Journey in order to your Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (if ſuch happen) being ſo ſenſible of the too great expence you have been at already, in carefully diſcharging the Truſt and Confidence repoſed in You:</q> 
               <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by above Sixty, whoſe Worth and Loyalty deſerve Immortal Fame, and to be Recorded as an Honourable Example both now and hereafter, for all other Corporations; which being all the Advice I can give you in this Matter, I ſhall conclude with deſiring you not to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98338:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of well-doing, neither to be alarm'd or troubled at frequent Proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Diſſolutions; ſince if you perſiſt in the ſame ſteady courſe you have already begun, it will but fall more heavily upon the heads of thoſe that are the contrivers of theſe Miſunderſtandings between his Gracious Majeſty, and his moſt faithful Subjects, for whoſe happy union, as well in opinion as affection, none can pray more heartily, than</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble Servant, and Fellow Subject, <hi>C. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>WHat I have here written, I do declare before Almighty God, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meerly from the earneſt Zeal and deſire I had of ſerving my King and Country; hoping by this timely caution to the Vulgar, to procure ſuch Senators, as might add to the Luſtre of our King, and ſafety of our Government, ſuch as might keep the Ballance even, and prevent our running either into Tyranny and Popety on the one hand, or into a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick and Fanaticiſm on the other: Such as might divert that Storm which threatens us, giving us that Peace and that Pranquility, which all men, who have either Eſtates or Families (like my ſelf) ure bound to pray for; ſuch as might render to <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Ceſars,</hi> and to God the things that are God's, and to the People the things that are the Peoples. For as I am govern'd by no private Faction or Intereſt, but purely by the dictates of my own Conſcience and Reaſon; ſo there is no Government but our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy, nor no Religion but what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that I hope ever to ſee prevail amongſt us, We have an old Proverb, and 'tis true as to our Condition, <hi>Over Shoes over Boots;</hi> ſo that now both City and Commons have proceeded thus far in oppoſing Popery, they cannot be ſafe but in doing more; for that 'twill be too late to repent, when a never-forgiving Popiſh Succeſſor ſhall come amongſt us, with that Text in his mouth of St. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>But thoſe mine enemies which would not that I ſhould reign over them, bring them hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſtay them before me.</hi> — Wherefore to prevent all this ruine and miſery, we cannot too often and too ſincerely pray for the Life, Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Proſperity of our Sovereign, <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> whom God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve both in this World and the next; which is the conſtant Prayer of his moſt obedient and faithful Subject,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98338:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
